Guide to the DeForest Douglas Diver Railroad Photographs, ca. 1870-1948
Diver, DeForest Douglas Railroad Photographs, ca. 1870-1948
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
DeForest Douglas Diver Railroad Photographs, ca. 1870-1948
1948
DeForest Douglas Diver, 1878-1958, Collector
3.4 cubic ft.
Original photographs, glass plates and other negatives, glossy prints.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Original photographs, glass plates and other negatives, and glossy prints, mainly of the New York, Ontario, and Western Railway, taken by Mr. Diver and others in Delaware, Madison, Oneida, Oswego, Otsego, and Sullivan Counties, New York.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
A collection of DeForest Douglas Diver, 1878-1958, railroad engineer and photographer, consisting of original photographs, glass plates and other negatives, and glossy prints, mainly of the New York, Ontario, and Western Railway. Subjects include employee groups, locomotives, passenger and freight cars, stations at Middletown and elsewhere, roundhouse and yards at Middleton, flooded and snowbound tracks, construction work and heavy equipment, the Hawk Mountain tunnel, and various wrecks. Photographs were taken by Mr. Diver and others at Cadosia, Cooks Falls, Fishs Eddy, Sidney, Delaware County; Morrisville, Oneida, Randallsville, Solsville, Madison County; Clinton, Oneida County; Constantia, Fulton, Oswego County; South New Berlin, Otsego County; Callicoon, Ferndale, Hankins, Hurleyville, Liberty, Summitville, Sullivan County.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Diver, DeForest Douglas, 1878-1958, Collector; New York, Ontario, and Western Railway Co.
Subjects:
Hawk Mountain Tunnel; Railroads--Accidents; Railroads--Construction; Railroads--Stations; Railroads--New York (State)
Places:
Delaware County (N.Y.); Madison County (N.Y.); Oneida County (N.Y.); Oswego County (N.Y.); Otsego County (N.Y.); Sullivan County (N.Y.)
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Available Copies:
Photographs from the collection have been digitized and are accessible through Cornell Library's Flickr site: http://www.flickr.com/photos/cornelluniversitylibrary/collections/72157621733952250/.
Photographs from the collection are also accessible through the RMC image portal..
SERIES LIST
Series I. Photograph files
Boxes 1-6
Series II. Negatives only
Box7
CONTAINER LIST
- Photographs
  - Class X #55277, (no gl. negative) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Railroad
    O&W
    Engine
    #360
    Builder
    Schen.
    Year
    1915
    Wheels
    2-10-2
    Fuel
    Coal
    Locale
    Yards with freight cars
  - Class X #55269, (no gl. negative) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    #352
    Yards with building
  - Mother Hubbard #771, (no gl. negative) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    #134
    Dickson
    1890
    2-6-0
    Railroad trestle with 3 crew
  - Mother Hubbard #2509, (no gl. negative) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    #201
    Cooke
    1900
    2-8-0
    Cadosia Trestle
  - [untitled], (no gl. negative) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    #85
    -
    1897
    Chair car "roundout"
  - Mother Hubbard #47072, (no gl. negative) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    #51
    1910
    0-6-0
    Crew--8 people
  - Mother Hubbard, Class C #1130, (no gl. negative) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    #74
    Brooks
    1886
    4-4-0
    Coal-wood
    Turntable
  - Mother Hubbard, Class G #1178, (no gl. negative) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    #75
    Wrecker
  - [untitled], (no gl. negative) (Box 1, Folder 9/453)
    #139
    1893
    2-6-2
  - [untitled], (no gl. negative) (Box 1, Folder 9/139)
  - [untitled] (Box 1, Folder 10/227)
    #227
    1911
  - [untitled] (Box 1, Folder 11/362)
    #362
  - [untitled] (Box 1, Folder 12/78)
    #78
    1887
  - [untitled] (Box 1, Folder 13/16)
    #16
    1898
  - [untitled] (Box 1, Folder 14/75)
    #14 [?read: 75]
  - [untitled] (Box 1, Folder 15/30)
    #30
    Baldwin
    1871
  - [untitled] (Box 1, Folder 16/5)
    #5
    Rhode I.
    1869
  - Water Tower & Mixed Units (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - [untitled] (Box 1, Folder 18/248)
    #248
    1901
    Middletown, NY
  - [untitled] (Box 1, Folder 19/303)
    #303
  - Rebuilt Rome Works, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 20/74)
  - Rebuilt from Baldwin #32, 1896, O&M Railroad (Box 1, Folder 21/11)
    #11
    Cooke/Baldwin
    1896
  - Class X Loco, "Bull Moose" (Box 1, Folder 22/358)
    #358
  - [untitled] (Box 1, Folder 23/1)
    #1
  - [untitled] (Box 1, Folder 24/1)
    1895
  - [untitled] (Box 1, Folder 25/0)
    Scrap Yard
  - Rebuilt #66, Middletown Shop as Inspection Car, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 26/26)
    #26
    New York
    1889
  - NY O&W Railroad Scrapped, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 27/103)
    #103
    Rhode Island
    1873
  - NY O&W Railroad "Franklin" (Box 1, Folder 28/33)
    #33
  - [untitled] (Box 1, Folder 29/7)
    #7
  - [untitled] (Box 2, Folder 30/304)
    #304
  - NY O&W RR (Box 2, Folder 31/1)
  - [untitled] (Box 2, Folder 32/51)
  - [untitled] (Box 2, Folder 32/247)
    #247
    1903
  - Inspection Car (Box 2, Folder 34/26)
    NY
  - Trestle (Box 2, Folder 35/Trestle)
    Cadosia, NY
  - Was # 78-2-6-0 Rebuilt (Box 2, Folder 36/49)
    #49
    Rd. Isl.
    1872
  - [untitled] (Box 2, Folder 37/41)
    #41
  - [untitled] (Box 2, Folder 38/105)
    #105
    NY Loco
  - [untitled] (Box 2, Folder 39/143)
    #143
  - [untitled] (Box 2, Folder 40/144)
    #144
  - [untitled] (Box 2, Folder 41/225)
    #225
    4-6-0
  - [untitled] (Box 2, Folder 42/1569)
    Not O&W
  - Rebuilt 2-6-0 (Box 2, Folder 43/31)
    #31
    1903/19
  - Snow Plow #3 (Box 2, Folder 44/3)
  - Roundhouse, Location Unknown, (No gl. negative) (Box 2, Folder 45/Round)
  - [untitled] (Box 2, Folder 46/134)
  - [untitled], (No negative; discrepancy between proof and cover photo) (Box 2, Folder 47/103)
  - Class X (Box 2, Folder 48/358)
  - Duplicate of #22, (No negative) (Box 2, Folder 48A/358)
  - Class Y (Box 2, Folder 49/401)
    #401
    1922
    4-8-2
  - Rods (Box 2, Folder 50/Rods)
  - Wheels (Box 2, Folder 50A/Rods)
  - [untitled] (Box 2, Folder 51)
    Cab Interior
    Gauges
  - [untitled], (Duplicate of #51) (Box 2, Folder 51/A)
  - Franklin, (Duplicate of #28, no negative) (Box 2, Folder 52/33)
    #52
  - [untitled], (Duplicate of #26, no negative) (Box 2, Folder 53/26)
  - Class Y (Box 2, Folder 54/405)
    #405
    1923
  - [untitled], (No negative) (Box 2, Folder 55/103)
  - [untitled], (Duplicate of #9, no negative) (Box 2, Folder 57/139)
  - Class Y (Box 2, Folder 58/405)
  - Railroad Station, So. Unadilla (Box 3, Folder 59/1)
  - Passenger-Freight Station, Rockland (Box 3, Folder 60/2)
  - Station, Guilford (Box 3, Folder 61/3)
  - Station, Rockland (Box 3, Folder 62/4)
  - Passenger Coach #85 (Box 3, Folder 63/5)
  - Passenger Coach #86 (Box 3, Folder 64/5A)
  - Passenger Coach #86 (Box 3, Folder 65/6)
  - Passenger Coach, Interior (Box 3, Folder 66/6A)
  - Passenger Train Wreck--Two People (Box 3, Folder 67/7)
  - Double Header--Snow Scene (Box 3, Folder 68/8)
  - Mixed Train, Railroad Bridge (Box 3, Folder 69/9)
  - Station, Milk Train Pick-up (Box 3, Folder 70/10)
  - Roundhouse & 23 Shopmen (Box 3, Folder 71/11)
  - Locomotive, Coming Around the Bend (Box 3, Folder 72/12)
  - Crossing & Two Freight Cars (Box 3, Folder 73/13)
  - Railroad Crossing, Three Tracks (Box 3, Folder 74/14)
  - Crossing & Two Freight Cars (Box 3, Folder 75/15)
  - Repair Shop & Two Men (Box 3, Folder 76/16)
  - Locomotive Wreck, Frame Remains (Box 3, Folder 77/17)
  - Locomotive Wreck, Water Tank (Box 3, Folder 78/17A)
  - Trucks (Rt. Side Cable) (Box 3, Folder 79/18)
  - Trucks (End View) (Box 3, Folder 80/18A)
  - Trucks (Left Side), (No negative) (Box 3, Folder 81/18B)
  - Trucks (Left Side, Building View), (No negative) (Box 3, Folder 82/18C)
  - Grade Crossing & Track Workers (Box 3, Folder 5/1)
  - Grade Crossing, Cameraman, Horse & Buggy (Box 3, Folder 5/2)
  - Country Road and Crossing (Box 3, Folder 5/3)
  - Railroad Shops and Two Workers (Box 3, Folder 5/4)
  - Roadhouse and Eight Locos (Box 3, Folder 5/5)
  - Roadhouse Workers and Transfer Table (Box 4, Folder 5/6)
  - Railroad Trestle (Modern) (Box 4, Folder 5/7)
  - Railroad Trestle (Old) (Box 4, Folder 5/8)
  - Railroad Trestle (With Man) (Box 4, Folder 5/9)
  - Railroad Track, Curve and Flat Cars (Box 4, Folder 5/10)
  - Wrecked Bridge & Coal Hoppers (Box 4, Folder 5/11)
  - Wrecked Bridge & Coal Cars (Box 4, Folder 5/12)
  - Wrecked Bridge & Coal Cars (Box 4, Folder 5/13)
  - Wrecked Bridge & O&W Car (Box 4, Folder 5/14)
  - Railroad Trestle (Box 4, Folder 5/15)
  - Railroad Trestle (High) (Box 4, Folder 5/16)
  - Rural Track Scene 2 (Box 4, Folder 5/17)
  - Rural Track Scene (Box 4, Folder 5/18)
  - Railroad Crossing with Man (Box 4, Folder 5/19)
  - Rural Track Scene 3 (Box 4, Folder 5/20)
  - Track Workers (6) (Box 4, Folder 5/21)
  - Track Plotting (Two Men) (Box 4, Folder 5/22)
  - Railroad Track Along River (Box 4, Folder 5/23)
  - Repairing Trestle (Box 4, Folder 5/24)
  - Repairing Trestle 2 (Box 4, Folder 5/25)
  - Watchman's Shed & Two Tracks (Box 4, Folder 5/26)
  - Rural Crossing (Box 4, Folder 5/27)
  - Coal Storage Yard, Middletown (Box 4, Folder 5/28)
  - Track and Bridge (Box 4, Folder 5/29)
  - Rural Scene (Box 4, Folder 5/30)
  - Railroad Scene (Box 4, Folder 5/31)
  - Engine #1 and Scrap (Box 4, Folder 5/32)
  - Engine and Wreck (Box 4, Folder 5/33)
  - Railroad Scene Along Hudson River, Coal Cars (Box 4, Folder 5/34)
  - Railroad Trestle for Coal Loading; Oswego, New York (Box 4, Folder 5/35)
  - Coal Loading and Ships; Oswego, NY (Box 4, Folder 5/36)
  - Coal Loading with Small Loco; Oswego, NY (Box 4, Folder 5/37)
  - Railroad Crossing, Rural Scene (Box 4, Folder 5/38)
  - Railroad Trestle, Carbondale (Looking North) (Box 4, Folder 5/39)
  - Railroad Yards; O&W Spur; Maybrook Yards, NYNH&H (Box 4, Folder 5/40)
  - Railroad Tracks (2) & Crossing; Shed (Box 4, Folder 5/41)
  - Railroad Crossing & Hand-Car Handle (Box 4, Folder 5/42)
  - Railroad Crossing & Hand-Car #2 (Box 4, Folder 5/43)
  - More Track Workers (Box 4, Folder 5/44)
  - Track Along River (Box 4, Folder 5/45)
  - River Road and Railroad Track, (Duplicate of 5/23) (Box 5, Folder 5/46)
  - More H Street With Circus Sign (Box 5, Folder 5/A)
  - Hurleyville Street Scene (Box 5, Folder 5/B)
  - Hurleyville Street (Box 5, Folder 5/C)
  - Old House, (Glass negative only) (Box 5, Folder 5/D)
  - Old House With People (Box 5, Folder 5/E)
  - Freight Ship Pueblo, *No 5/F listed (Box 5, Folder 5/G*)
  - Locomotives 54-55-56 and Crews (Box 5, Folder 201)
  - Loco 227 & Passenger Train (Box 5, Folder 202)
  - Work Train at Clinton, NY (Box 5, Folder 203)
  - Work Train with Shay Loco? (Box 5, Folder 204)
  - Cornfield Meet (Box 5, Folder 205)
  - Loco 256 & Crew (Box 5, Folder 206)
  - Loco 153 & Workmen (Box 5, Folder 207)
  - Unknown Loco & Caboose 8146 (Box 5, Folder 208)
  - Railroad Station; Middletown, NY (Box 5, Folder 209)
  - D&H Canal; Summitville, NY (Box 5, Folder 210)
  - Tender 254 and a bunch of men (Box 5, Folder 211)
  - Train Wreck (Box 5, Folder 212)
  - Train Wreck (Box 5, Folder 213)
  - Railroad Yards, O&W; Middletown, NY? (Box 5, Folder 214)
  - Inspection Car #3 (Box 5, Folder 215)
  - Inspection Car #20 (Box 5, Folder 216)
  - Train 32, Loco 172 & Crew & Octagon Water Tower (Box 5, Folder 217)
  - Locomotive & Crew (Box 5, Folder 218)
  - Loco #3 and Two Wooden Coaches (Box 5, Folder 219)
  - Loco 14, Crew & Watertower (Box 5, Folder 220)
  - Loco 42, Passenger Train, Pat Diver; Weehawken, N.J. (Box 5, Folder 221)
  - Loco 204 (Box 5, Folder 222)
  - Loco 457 (Box 5, Folder 223)
  - Loco 360 (Box 5, Folder 224)
  - Loco 362 (Box 5, Folder 225)
  - Loco 69 & Engineer (Box 5, Folder 226)
  - Passenger Coach, Wooden #25 (Box 5, Folder 227)
  - Diesel 321, Wreck (Box 5, Folder 228)
  - Inspection Car #38 (Box 5, Folder 229)
  - Diesel 117 (Box 6, Folder 230)
  - Diesel 117 (Box 6, Folder 231)
  - Coach Combination #802 (Box 6, Folder 232)
  - Brill Car (Box 6, Folder 233)
  - Diesel 103 (Box 6, Folder 234)
  - Train Wreck (Box 6, Folder 235)
  - Train Wreck (Box 6, Folder 236)
  - More Train Wreck (Box 6, Folder 237)
  - Wreck (Box 6, Folder 238)
  - Wreck Loco 140 (Box 6, Folder 239)
  - Wreck Loco 161 (Box 6, Folder 240)
  - Wreck (Box 6, Folder 241)
  - Wreck (Box 6, Folder 242)
  - Wreck (Box 6, Folder 243)
  - Wreck, Boiler Explosion (Box 6, Folder 244)
  - Gravity Railroad; Honsdale, PA; September, 1899 (Box 6, Folder 245)
  - untitled (White fence with train tracks in background), [Glass neg. only] (Box 6, Folder no number)
  - untitled (Bridge), [Glass neg. only] (Box 6, Folder no number)
  - untitled (White fence with train tracks in background, train approaching), [Glass neg. only] (Box 6, Folder no number)
  - untitled (White fence with train tracks in background, train approaching), [Glass neg. only] (Box 6, Folder no number)
  - untitled (Photographed painting of four men), [Glass neg. only] (Box 6, Folder no number)
  - untitled (Record of train dimensions, letterhead; American Locomotive Co.), [Glass neg. only] (Box 6, Folder no number)
  - untitled (Photograph of award presented to John M. Wilson on 12/26/1897), [Glass neg. only] (Box 6, Folder no number)
- Negatives
  - Santa Fe type Class X, Middletown water column in foreground, Eng. 352, 2-10-2; glass (Box 7)
  - Order card for NYO&W Class Y mountain type engine, Eng. 401-410, 4-8-2; glass (Box 7)
  - Pop Weehawker, DeForest (Pat) Diver, 1, glass (Box 7)
  - Canal towpath, Summitville, N.Y., seventeen mile level at Summitville, N.Y., glass (Box 7)
  - Minnewaska Road (3 glass plates), glass (Box 7)
  - Unidentified (2 glass plates), glass (Box 7)
  - Two Negatives (Box 7)
    - Camelback Dickson, Sam St. John, Bob Oles "Dichen" at Northfield Tunnel, Eng. 151, 2-8-0; film (Box 7)
    - Harvey and Lozier on inspection, Eng. #26; film (Box 7)
  - Possibly Sidney Station, film (Box 7)
  - Mayfield Yard Shop buildings, Mayfield, Pa., film (Box 7)
  - Box cars, furniture & auto cars [wreck] (2 negs & 2 prints), 9200-9751; film (Box 7)
  - Camelback Mogul with baggage, RPO, & coach on trestle, Eng. 246, 2-6-0; film (Box 7)
  - Trestle (2 negs.), film (Box 7)
  - Five views, type Sante Fe, brand new 1916 (5 negs.), Eng. 351, 2-10-2; film (Box 7)
  - Shop crew, locomotive shop, Middletown, N.Y. (8 negs.), film (Box 7)
  - Cadosia, N.Y. yards, coal storage, trestle (3 negs.), film (Box 7)
  - Mogul type Camelback, Eng. 274, 2-6-0; film (Box 7)
  - Wreck at Borden's condensed milk plant (2 negs.), film (Box 7)
  - Switching milk cars on New Berlin Branch?, Engine 217; film (Box 7)
  - Northfield Tunnel portal, film (Box 7)
  - Scenes along the right-of-way and the D&H Canal (4 negs.), film (Box 7)
  - Steam derrick #1, film (Box 7)
  - Three Negatives (Box 7)
    - Scene on Scranton Division near Orson, Pa. cut where heavy drifts of snow accumulated to be plowed out, film (Box 7)
    - Orson, Pa. double tracked with siding going to ice house, film (Box 7)
    - Orson, Pa. looking northeast toward creamery and ice house, film (Box 7)
  - Steam derrick #2 and trailer flat (2 negs.), film (Box 7)
  - Coaling tower at Mayfield Yard, Mayfield, PA. and ash pit, film (Box 7)
  - Cadosia Station and tracks, Cadosia, N.Y., film (Box 7)
  - Unidentified (32 negs.), film (Box 7)
ADDITIONAL INFORMATION
Supplemental Lists
List of N.Y.O. & W. engines usually with a coal car in the Diver RR Collection, glossy print and glass plate of each; compiled by N. Dean, 4-6-66. In Box [ ] unless noted otherwise.
Engine #
1
5
11
26 [28]
30
31
41
49
51
74
75
78
103
105
139
143
225
227
247
248
303
304
352
358
360
362
401
405
453
Franklin
and a few unnumbered engines.
List of N.Y.O. & W. vestibule chair (passenger) cars in the Diver RR Collection, glossy print and glass plate of each; compiled by N. Dean, 4-6-66.
Vestibule chair cars #
85
86
List of boxcar photographs in the Diver RR Collection; compiled by N. Dean, 2/25/64
One boxcar in background; # impossible to read.
glass plate
Long line of boxcars at station; # impossible to read; incl. Lehigh Valley car; neg. # 40.
glass plate
N.Y.O. & W. boxcar 2211.
glass plate
N.Y.O. & W. boxcar 2211 (second view).
glass plate
N.Y.O. & W. engine 360 and boxcar (?) 15432; neg. #E17.
glass plate & print
Boxcar 2212.
glass plate
N.Y.O. & W. boxcar 2816 with engine 99.
print
N.Y.O. & W. boxcar 2327.
print
Train on track; engine, boxcar, and 2 passenger cars; no numbers [797 on back of picture].
print
N.Y.O. & W. boxcar 9257 at great distance.
picture postcard
N.Y.O. & W. boxcar 9623 with engine 362; neg. #E16.
glass plate
N.Y.O. & W. boxcar 9584 [incorrectly captioned as "91 - Buell Brothers' Taxicab, Norwich, N.Y."].
print
Additional information on contents of Diver RR Photograph Collection
Negative and print of picture of inspection locomotive #28 made, June 26, 1963; print sent of Lucius Beebe (see general corres. file) and negative filed in collection.
Collection does NOT include a picture of inspection locomotive #28 (see letter from Leonard Rice, 9/7/63).
For checklist of boxcar photos made 2/64, see attached list.
For checklist of N.Y.O. & W. engine and vestibule chair car photos made 4/66, see attached list.
Additional Description
Report of the Curator and Archivist, 1958-62